<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Fiat justitia &amp; ruat cœlum, or, Somewhat offer'd in defence of the imperial crown of England and its successor in answer to a speech pretended to be spoken in the honourable House of Commons, upon the reading the bill against the D. / by a true Englishman.</title>
            <author>True Englishman.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 24 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41261</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F845</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R35675</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15538718</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15538718</idno>
            <idno type="VID">103638</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A41261)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 103638)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1149:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Fiat justitia &amp; ruat cœlum, or, Somewhat offer'd in defence of the imperial crown of England and its successor in answer to a speech pretended to be spoken in the honourable House of Commons, upon the reading the bill against the D. / by a true Englishman.</title>
                  <author>True Englishman.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>The bill referred to is the Exclusion Bill directed against the Duke of York, afterwards King James II--LC in OCLC.</note>
                  <note>"A speech in the House of Commons upon reading the bill against the D": p. 4.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>James --  II, --  King of England, 1633-1701.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Kings and rulers --  Succession.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:103638:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Fiat Juſtitia, &amp; Ruat Coelum. Or, Somewhat offer'd in Deſence of the <hi>Imperial Crown of England.</hi> And its SUCCESSOR. In Anſwer to a SPEECH, pretended to be ſpoken in the Honourable Houſe of Commons, upon Reading the BILL againſt the D. <hi>By a true Engliſhman.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IT is not long ago, ſince a mighty Orator, Lawyer, Logician, and what not, moſt ſtrenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly undertook, for weighty Conſiderations, to overthrow all Law and Logick, and by tacking of inconſequent words (as he us'd to do Bills) together, to ſhew the World how zealouſly and boldly he could ſpeak No ſence. This ſame Sir <hi>Formal Trifle,</hi> who in his <hi>Exordium</hi> very gravely tells his Auditory, there is a neceſſity of ſpeaking their minds in a Grand Affair, that concerns the King and Kingdom, would fain make them believe, that he is a going to ſay ſomewhat for the King, (as he expreſſes it) and ſo to prove himſelf an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Loyaliſt, makes a Speech for the King, in oppoſition to the Royal Will. He knows very well, the King has often declar'd, That he would never do any thing that might hinder the Succeſſion to the Crown in the right Line; yet ſtill he muſt try his faculty in Rhetorick, and ſay ſomewhat for the King. Now either this kind Gentleman imagines, he can be a greater Friend to the King, than the King to himſelf, or elſe his Wit and Eloquence have ſpoil'd his Memory in the Law; for there he may find, the King is no <hi>Minor,</hi> but that he has always years enough to ſpeak for himſelf. But 'tis no matter what he means; let it be what it will, he muſt needs be a good States-man, that utters himſelf, like a Spout, for the King and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; eſpecially in a buſineſs of ſuch importance, as the ſecuring of Religion. And indeed this Theologico-Political Orator of ours, takes the true way to ſecure Religion; for he will not let any body enjoy ſo much as his Birth-right, if it be poſſible, that ſuch a thing may be dangerous to Religion. Now truly here we may take occaſion to conſider in this weighty Matter, what manner of Religion this good Gentleman would ſecure: Is it the Creed of <hi>Knipperdolling?</hi> truly I am not certain, he does not mean ſo. Is it the truly modern Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of <hi>Geneveſian John?</hi> it may be ſo either, for ought I know; but that it is not the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> I dare boldly, and with the higheſt zeal affirm. I cannot tell what he ſuppoſes, or what the Spirit within him dictates; but, if his Policy have not o'recome his Religion, he muſt confeſs, that neither the avow'd Doctrine of this Church, nor any juſt and rational Interpretation of Scripture, can induce him to think, that Religion is to be ſecur'd by perverting the univerſal principle of all Nations, and acting contrary to the expreſs Word of God. But indeed ſo zealous is this paſſionate Advocate for his Religion, <hi>i. e.</hi> his Eſtate, (for ſo he afterwards explains himſelf) that to ſecure his own Right, he will not be diſcouraged by the ſeeming oppoſition of any, that another has; no, though his own King's Succeſſor, whoſe Orator he has lately made himſelf.</p>
            <p>My Lord Chancellor, he tells us, lately told them, that <hi>This was the Time;</hi> and he very wiſely thinks, that he may make uſe of this Saying upon all occurrences, like <hi>Teage</hi> in the <hi>Committee,</hi> ſo he has but a Letter, he cares not who it's written to. And then beſides that, he preſumes to be as good a Politician as my Lord, (how arrogantly, the World may judge) and to apply thoſe words (which his Lordſhip maturely brought forth) to the crude Notions of his own raw Brains; he goes on and comments upon what my Lord ſaid, and makes his Lordſhip's Time (long enough for deliberation, and profound Thoughts) to ſhrink and dwin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle into an inconſiderable, inconſiderate Moment. But truly a Moment is of a duration ſufficient to ſpeak all his Reaſon in, and if diviſible, would lie at leaſt one half upon our hands, ready to be imploy'd in any other kind of Jargon. And now he has found the Critical Minute of action, he as judiciouſly adviſes not to let it ſlip, but with a diſpatch as quick as Thought, immediately reſolve upon his Counſel: For if you do not, you are under a great hazard, that your Children may curſe you, nay, be bound to curſe you, that's more. A ſtrange obligation this upon Children, that they ſhould be bound to curſe their Forefathers for doing Juſtice even to an Heathen: For ſurely this Gentleman's Children (eſpecially if they are not truly his) may eaſily come to know, that Right and Wrong were never reſtrain'd to this or that ſort of men but common and diffus'd to all Mankind. No, they'l certainly conſider, that there's no
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:103638:2"/> reaſon they ſhould curſe their Fathers, for not making a Law to dis-inherit an Heir; for it will be naturally ſuggeſted to them, that it might have been their own caſe. Oh! but the <hi>great good</hi> that follows upon this however unnatural Injury, is no leſs, than the ſecuring of Religion. So then, we may <hi>do ill, that good may come on't.</hi> I proteſt, but that this Gentleman is a Member of the Honourable Houſe, I ſhould have taken him for a Jeſuit, that had onely diſguis'd himſelf under a pretence for Proteſtant Religion. For I appeal to the whole Houſe, if this be not a Jeſuitical practice, to cut off a King, or (which is worſe) dethrone him, and yet more barbarouſly let him live, meerly becauſe he is an Heretick to their Principles. He that relies upon ſuch Maximes, makes it utterly impoſſible ever to eſtabliſh any, much leſs the <hi>Protestant</hi> Religion. I admire what wonders this worthy Patriot thinks the <hi>D.</hi> can do when he comes to the Crown; can he make Laws, or alter the Conſtitution of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, without the conſent of a Parliament? He does not think ſo, I am ſure. Why then cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, he muſt believe the whole Nation is inclined to Popery, or otherwiſe he could never imagine a Popiſh Succeſſor to be ſo formidable a Gyant as he makes him. But let him live where he will, in the City or Countrey, I don't doubt but he hears arguments enough, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade any reaſonable Creature, that 'tis a difficulty to bring Popery into <hi>England,</hi> next to that of tranſlating <hi>Rome</hi> to <hi>London.</hi> Can he think, that the King's being a Papiſt will be a juſt reaſon why the People muſt be ſo too? when ſo many and the ſame Laws continue in force againſt that kind of men? If we for fear of the Tyranny of the See of <hi>Rome</hi> ſtealing upon us, would take way the Kings Succeſſion, what kind of Elective Monarchy would this be, that for ſo many Ages has ran down in a continu'd ſtream of Inheritable Blood, without any inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption? At that rate, when ever the Speech-makers in the Houſe of Commons could make the reſt fear any remote poſſibility of danger from the King's Succeſſors perſwaſion (be it what it would be) the Crown muſt be ſtraight-way ſettled upon ſome other (Chriſtian or no Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, all's one, ſo no Papiſt) and ſo the right Heir be dis-inherited, for not ſerving the People with more reverence than his Maker. There's no man but would willingly enjoy the freedom of his Religion, and would hardly think it juſt to have his Eſtate taken from him for it; how then can any one ſay, 'Tis fit that the Deſcent of a Crown ſhould be impeded for an opinion which was precedently taken up. If it were ſuch a crime to be of this or that Opinion, ſo high, as to make a man liable to be dis-inherited, how could any one be ſure of what he has? For be it once granted, that the <hi>D</hi> may be cut off from his Inheritance for his preſent Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, then the reaſon will be equally urgent againſt any other as him. For whoſoever comes to the Crown with a new or an old Religion, is as obnoxious to this Exception as a <hi>Romaniſt.</hi> The onely objection againſt the <hi>D.</hi> that can poſſibly be made, is, that he would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to propagate his Perſwaſion; who would not? who does not? This very Orator would, and does moſt vehemently preſs the Houſe to believe what he ſays, and dares do't, nay, thinks he's bound in Conſcience to do it, <hi>i.e.</hi> to ſettle his Religion by ſuch means as none would do, but ſuch a Perſon as is acted by Zeal and Intereſt, mix'd with ſome Vanity and Popularity. The Argument would return too ſmartly upon him, if we ſhould ſay, Therefore a Presbyterian may loſe his Right, becauſe of his being ſo. But beſides the want of Reaſon, I find a great ſcarcity of common ſenſe in what this Politician ſays, <hi>It will be utterly impoſſible to ſecure the Proteſtant Religion under a Popiſh Succeſsor, unleſs you totally diſable him to inherit,</hi> &amp;c. How is he <hi>Popiſh Succeſſor,</hi> under whom, &amp;c. if he be <hi>totally diſabled</hi> to inherit? And then the connection of what follows is ſo natural, — <hi>unleſs you diſable him to inherit, — and the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny of the See of</hi> Rome <hi>will infallibly ſteal upon us.</hi> I confeſs I cannot tell when, no more than he can: For I muſt tell him boldly, that if he means under a Popiſh Succeſſor, it is non-ſenſe: upon non-ſenſe: For firſt he ſays, <hi>A Succeſſor under whom,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſhould be utterly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to inherit,</hi> &amp;c. and then after that, <hi>The Tyranny will ſteal upon us infallibly,</hi> becauſe the Man from whom we ought to fear is totally diſabled to inherit. But whether it hang to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether or no, 'tis all one, it ſounds well enough, and looks like an happy Thought for our ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: And who can blame a man for an incoherence, as long as he loves his Countrey: It may be he was in a Rapture, or a fit of the higheſt Zeal; and then one may be allowed to forget him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, having ſo great a reſpect to the Proteſtant Religion.</p>
            <p>The next conſideration in this weighty matter is, that a King is not reſtrainable by Penal Laws, but, like <hi>Samſon,</hi> can break through them; and therefore we muſt clip his Locks, that is, take his Crown or his Head from him, if we can poſſibly ſurmiſe that he would pull down the Temple. Truly this Gentleman would have made a better <hi>Philiſtin</hi> than a Proteſtant. Oh! but how can one blame him for his zealous fear, when he has lately ſeen <hi>Coleman</hi>'s Ghoſt, dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully reciting a terrible Maxim, That the Papiſts would get the upper hand, if they ſtood up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on an equal foot; and if ſo, (and ſo it muſt needs be, if Mr. <hi>Coleman</hi>'s infallible Spirit ſaid it) why then, to ſecure our own Lives and Eſtates, make ſure of the <hi>Duke</hi>'s, let him not have his Right, if ours may be indangered by ſuffering him to have his. This is a Maxim of ours (Mr. <hi>Coleman</hi>) and ſo there's a <hi>Rowland</hi> for your <hi>Oliver.</hi> I ſay, this is true Religion, beſides the Policy of it. For look you, Religion teaches to ſecure Religion, and I my ſelf have found out a way to effect it. The invention indeed is very new, but 'tis the better for that, and the more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and though it ſeem a little odd at firſt, yet if a man do but conſider, that Religion is
<pb facs="tcp:103638:2"/> concern'd, why then he may eaſily imagine, that Religion can be againſt nothing that is done in favour of Religion. There 'tis then. We to prevent Maſſacres may do worſe; that is, calmly and adviſedly, by the Sanction of Law, take away a Prince's Inheritance, leſt in his Reign there ſhould happen a Riot, or an Hurly-burly among the People. Is it reaſonable, that any King ſhould Rule us, that will not promiſe to make <hi>Westminſter-Hall</hi> of no uſe, or ſwear at his Coronation, that no Popiſh Prieſt or Laick ſhall ever moleſt, trouble, or annoy any of the King's Liege People with any Diſputes or Controverſies in or about Religion; or that any Jeſuit, in any diſguiſe whatſoever, ſhall ever ſet foot upon his Majeſty's Land of <hi>Great Britain?</hi> For, Sir, I muſt tell you, unleſs it were ſo, I know no cauſe why we may not chooſe another man that can and will do ſo. Poor man! how pale he looks at the apparition of <hi>Cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>'s Maxim? Truly though he pretends zeal for the Proteſtant Religion yet me-thinks this argues him to have but a very mean opinion of it; and I ſuſpect him for a Jeſuit now more than before, becauſe he believes ſo ſtedfaſtly in <hi>Coleman</hi>'s Maxim. Surely he could not give any great credit to <hi>Coleman,</hi> if he had thoſe honourable thoughts which he pretends of the Proteſtant Religion, nor ever think the ruine of it ſo feaſible, if he were ſo zealous for the ſecuring of it. And now he a ſecond time brings my Lord Chancellor before us, and by pretty alluſions would make his Lordſhip's Speech as inſignificant as that of himſelf. Now 'tis a <hi>Fig-leafe,</hi> and in the ſame breath, <hi>Leaf-gold,</hi> and to both theſe he allows ſome uſe and flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering Ornament, (more than my Lord can do for his Speech.) But he has a third Metaphor, which does my Lord a great deal of honour before he's aware on t; 'Tis like a <hi>Mother</hi> that has a froward Child, he ſays. And truly I am much of his mind; for 'tis indeed <hi>as froward</hi> and humorſome a Brat as e'er poor Mother had; it wou'd have ſo many Toys and Jim-cracks, that ſhe cannot poſſibly pleaſe it. Indeed the peeviſh Chit ſcarce knows what to ask, or at leaſt is uſed to make his demands after ſuch a manner that 'tis impoſſible the good Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman ſhould anſwer his deſire, but with ſome diſparagement to Maternal Dignity. Yet ſtill there is a neceſſity that his Requeſts muſt be ſatisfied, let them be what they will, juſt or unjuſt, againſt Nature or otherwiſe, all's one, Child muſt be pleaſed: And ſo the neceſſity of the Bill is Mathematically demonſtrated. But that is not all, unleſs you can demonſtrate the good that may accrue by it, (for there is a difference between the Bill and its Goodneſs) and ſo conſequently make the World your Proſelytes. Now to perform this mighty task, thus I begin.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I grant, that there is a <hi>great evil</hi> that will enſue upon it, but not <hi>half</hi> ſo great as the <hi>good</hi> that may <hi>come by it:</hi> and therefore as long as 'tis no otherwiſe, it will be allowed by the whole Nation, and they'll eaſily forget a trifling ill (of taking the Sight of a private Prince from him or ſo) when they ſee it is a ſo far greater good that is conſequent thereupon. And that it is ſo, is very plain; for we ſhall <hi>ſecure our Eſtates,</hi> and that by onely taking away the Duke's, <hi>i.e.</hi> killing him; for to take away his Eſtate (according to this Gentleman) is to kill him, and worſe, admitting that he is an <hi>Engliſh-man.</hi> But it may be this Demonſtrator fancies him no <hi>Engliſh-man,</hi> ſince he went into <hi>Flanders,</hi> but that he has alter'd his Nature with his Religion. Truly that would be an excellent Demonſtration, if he could make it. But I find he is a very young Demonſtrator; for, if you obſerve, his Demonſtration goes off in a bare opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and does not at all compel our aſſent. But if he cannot demonſtrate ſo well, yet he can put Caſes, like <hi>Littleton.</hi> Thus, if the King be a <hi>Lunatick</hi> in an Elective Monarchy) and cannot do the Kingdom any good, the Subjects may chooſe another as in the caſe of <hi>Portugal</hi>) therefore by parity of reaſon, if a King's Heir be ſo mad as o be of any Perſwaſion different from the People, (in an Hereditary Government, as in <hi>England</hi>) the People may chooſe another Heir to ſerve the Kingdom; for that is the main reaſon why he muſt be turn'd out, to wit, becauſe he cannot <hi>ſerve the Nation.</hi> A Very fine expreſſion for one that ſpeaks for the King, and like a Lawyer too. Now as to the point of Law, it ſeems very ſtrange, that it ſhould be Rebellion to riſe up againſt the King, and yet no offence to <hi>dis-inherit him.</hi> It was indeed En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted in the 13th. of the Queen, That whoſoever ſhould affirm, that the Laws and Statutes did not bind the Right of the Crown, and the Deſcent, Limitation, Inheritance, or Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance thereof, ſhould be guilty of High Treaſon; and not onely of a <hi>Praemunire,</hi> as this Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torical Lawyer, in his merciful Ignorance, leſſens the guilt. But the Act is expired, and no other ſince made that I hear of; if there were, I know of no man that would be ſo ſottiſhly mad as to offend againſt it; for it is not the queſtion now, whether the King and Parliament can politically, but whether they can Morally do what this Gentleman propoſes, without any violence to Juſtice and Religion. The 35th. of <hi>H.</hi> 8. limits the Crown to <hi>Edward, Mary, Elizabeth,</hi> and their Lawful Heirs, becauſe they were of Inheritable Blood; and for lack of ſuch Iſſue, that then the King <hi>H.</hi> 8. might diſpoſe of it by Will, or Letters Patents, for the avoiding (I humbly conceive) of ſtrife that might ariſe, among thoſe that ſhould afterwards pretend any Right; but it was never deſigned by him or any other, that a Lawful Heir ſhould be excluded from ſucceeding, nor is there any reaſon in it, let who will go about to <hi>demonſtrate, opine,</hi> or <hi>ſay it.</hi> That Heathen, I am ſure, would have made a better Chriſtian, as he was a better Lawyer than our Orator, who more agreeably to the intent of all Laws, ſaid, <hi>Fiat juſtitia, &amp; ruat Coelum.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:103638:3"/>
            <head>A <hi>SPEECH</hi> in the Houſe of <hi>COMMONS,</hi> Upon Reading the <hi>Bill</hi> againſt the D.</head>
            <p>WE have now the weightieſt matter under our Conſideration, that ever came before us, therefore we ought with the higheſt Zeal to ſpeak our minds boldly for the King and Kingdom: for as the matter is of no leſs importance, than to ſecure our Religion to Poſterity, ſo much the rather ſhould we apply our ſelves to manifeſt that we will not be diſcouraged by any ſéeming oppoſition whatſoever.</p>
            <p>But as the Lord Chancellor lately told us, <hi>This is the Time,</hi> ſo I muſt repeat it, <hi>That it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the Time;</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>the Moment:</hi> which if we ſhould ſuffer to ſlip from us, it may ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be in our power to regain, and then our Children may be bound to Curſe us: for I muſt tell you, That it will be utterly impoſſible ever to ſecure the Proteſtant Religion under a <hi>Popiſh</hi> Succeſſor, unleſs you do totally diſable him to inherit theſe Proteſtant Countries; and the Tyranny of the Sée of <hi>Rome</hi> will infallibly ſteal upon us.</p>
            <p>For to think to reſtrain a King under the power of a Penal Law, thereby to ſecure Religion, is no more than to bind <hi>Sampſon</hi> with Cords, who as ſoon as 'tis ſaid, <hi>The Philiſtins are upon thee,</hi> will break them all in pieces, and carry the Gates away with him, and leave you open to the invaſion of the Enemy; nothing therefore can be able to ſecure us, but to clip his Locks: For if the Papiſts do at this time deſign to ſubbert our Religion under a Proteſtant Prince, how much more will they deſign againſt us under a Popiſh Succeſſor? What will not the Prieſts and Ieſuits undertake, to procure our Deſtruction, when they ſhall have the favour of the Prince, and are ſecured that the Laws and Statutes made againſt them, ſhall not be put in Execution? for 'tis <hi>Coleman's</hi> Maxim, That if the Popiſh Religion ſtood upon an equal foot with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant, the Popiſh Religion would get the better, as they would manage it; and then our Eſtates could never be ſecure, no, nor our very Lives; and Proteſtants would be diſcouraged, and hardly dare to ſpeak their minds; and Maſſacres may be as frequent and as great here, as they were formerly at <hi>Paris:</hi> So that 'tis clear we can never reſtrain him.</p>
            <p>The Lord Chancellor in his Spéech tells you, That when His Majeſty ſhall happen to dye, we ſhall have a convenient time to ſettle Religion and the Nation. Let me aſk you, Muſt we act with the Succeſſor, or without him? if we act with him, he will never conſent to any thing we ſhall do againſt him; if without him, we act as a Commonwealth, and that he will never ſuffer, but perhaps, will ſend his Guards, and turn us out of Doors, and what will become of us then?</p>
            <p>One Reaſon laid down to us likewiſe is, That it is impoſſible for a Succeſſor to raiſe Money, but by Conſent of Parliament: that point may be eaſily anſwered by us, There are many ſmall Burroughs and Towns who chooſe us, where there are but few Voices; how eaſie is it to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe thoſe Votes by Money? if he ſhould lay out Ten or Twenty thouſand pound for the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe, they would ſoon give it him again; and then the whole Nation will be ruin'd without Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption. The Spéech of the Lord Chancellor is only a Fig-leaf to cover our Nakedneſs, or rather Leaf-Gold to flatter us; or like a Mother who having a froward Child, and upon neceſſity muſt do ſomething to pacifie it, ſhe gives it any thing ſhe hath, but lets it kéep it no longer than ſhe pleaſes.</p>
            <p>Now I have ſhewn you the neceſſity of this Bill, let us next conſider, that the good which will come by it, is far greater than the evil that can enſue upon it; which I will thus demonſtrate: If we give way to a Popiſh Succeſſor, we give away Religion, and have Popiſh Tyranny for a recompence; And then conſequently, our Eſtates will be taken away, and for an <hi>Engliſh</hi> man to loſe his Eſtate, is worſe than to loſe his Life, ſince he muſt continue in perpetual Bondage, and be worſe than a Captive ſlave, and ſhall be Prieſt-ridden every day; therefore in my opinion, it is far better for us to reſolve to maintain our Religion, and to ſecure our ſelves by oppoſing any violence that ſhall be offered to us from abroad, than to be in danger of having our Throats cut every moment, by thoſe that ſhall be amongſt us.</p>
            <p>Now let us conſider, whether this may be effected by Law, or out of neceſſity. I will put the Caſe, That if a Prince be born to a Kingdom who is either Lunatick, or otherwiſe diſabled to do the Kingdom any good, ſhall not the Subjects in this Caſe procéed to chooſe another who may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Kingdom, when otherwiſe i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> muſt of neceſſity periſh? as lately in the Caſe of <hi>Portugal,</hi> they choſe another to ſuccéed, becauſe of the diſability of the former; And ſhall not we then diſable the Duke, who cannot poſſibly do the Nation any ſervice, his Principles being ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary and deſtructive to the Laws, Statutes and Conſtitutions of this Government, as nothing but ruine can enſue thereby?</p>
            <p>Now as to the Point of Law, I muſt ſay, that as for a private perſon to riſe againſt his Prince, is Rebellion; ſo on the contrary, when there is an Act of Parliament to diſable him, and that upon ſuch good grounds and reaſons as we have heard read againſt him this day, we ſhall be juſtified by all the World in oppoſing his Claim; and we have had Preſidents of this kind here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore. And it was enacted in Quéen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time, That thoſe who durſt any way diſpute that the King and Parliament could not appoint a Succeſſor, ſhould be guilty of a <hi>Praemunire.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:103638:4"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:103638:4"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
